<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The assembly-man written by John Birkenhead, in the year 1647.</title>
            <author>Birkenhead, John, Sir, 1616-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28203</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2963</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35660</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11699639</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11699639</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48253</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28203)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48253)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 808:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The assembly-man written by John Birkenhead, in the year 1647.</title>
                  <author>Birkenhead, John, Sir, 1616-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], 10-18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Davis ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681/2.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears in Wit and loyalty reviv'd ... London, 1682.</note>
                  <note>Possibly issued separately.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48253:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Aſſembly-man;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by Sir <hi>John Birkenhead;</hi> in the Year <hi>1647.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>
               <hi>ΘΕΟΦΡΑΣΤ. Χαρακτ ιγʹ περί ΠΕΡΙΕΡΓΙΑΣ.</hi>
            </bibl>
            <q>
               <hi>Δ</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>i.e.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>He ſeditiouſly ſtirs up men to fight: he'll teach others the way whereof himſelf is moſt ignorant; and perſuades men to take an Oath, becauſe himſelf had ſworn it before.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON, Printed for</hi> W. Davis, Anno Dom. <hi>1681/2.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:48253:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Pamphlet was torn from me by thoſe who ſay they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not rob, becauſe all is theirs. They found it where it ſlept ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years forgotten; but they 'waken'd it, and made falſe Tranſcripts. They <hi>Exciz'd</hi> what they liked not; ſo mangled and <hi>Reform'd,</hi> that 'twas no Character of an <hi>Aſſembler,</hi> but of themſelves. A Copy of that <hi>Reformling</hi> had crept to the Preſs. I ſeiz'd and ſtopt it, unwilling to Father other mens ſins. Here therefore you have it (as 'twas firſt ſcribled) without addition of a ſyllable; I wiſh I durſt ſay here's nothing lopt off. But men and manners are chang'd, at leaſt they ſay ſo. If yet this trifle ſeem born with teeth, you know whoſe hands were knuckle-deep in the blood of that renouned Chancellor of <hi>Oxon</hi> (Arch-biſhop <hi>LAUD</hi>) though when they cut up that great Martyr, his two greateſt Crimes were the two greateſt Glories <hi>Great Britain</hi> can boaſt of, <hi>St. Paul's Church</hi> and the <hi>Oxford Library.</hi> Where you find no coherence, remember this Paper hath ſuffer'd <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimation:</hi> Better times have made it worſe, and that's no fault of.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. Berkenhead.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:48253:2"/>
            <head>THE Aſſembly-man.</head>
            <p>AN <hi>Aſſembler</hi> is part of the <hi>State,'</hi> Chattels: nor <hi>Prieſt,</hi> nor <hi>Burgeſs,</hi> but a <hi>Participle</hi> that ſhark's upon both. He was choſen, as Sir <hi>Nathaniel,</hi> becauſe he knew leaſt of all his Profeſsion: not by the Votes of a Whole Dioceſe, but by one whole Parliament-man. He ha's ſate four years <hi>towards</hi> a new Religion, but in the interim left none at all: as his Maſters, the <hi>Commons</hi> had along Debate <hi>whether Canáles or no Candles,</hi> but all the mean while ſate ſtill in the Dark: And therefore when the Moon quits her old Light, and has acquir'd no new, Aſtronomeres ſay ſhe is in her <hi>Synodes,</hi> Shew me ſuch a Picture of <hi>Judas</hi> as the <hi>Aſſembler,</hi> (a grip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, falſe, Reforming Brother; rail's at <hi>Waſte</hi> ſpent upon the <hi>Anointed;</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutes moſt thoſe Hands which <hi>Ordain'd</hi> him; brings in <hi>men with ſwords and ſtates;</hi> and all for Money from the Honourable <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees:</hi>) One Touch more (a Line tyed to his Name-ſake <hi>Elder-tree</hi>) had made him <hi>Judas,</hi> Root and Branch. This <hi>Aſſembly</hi> at firſt was a full Century; which ſhould be reckon'd as the Scholiaſt's <hi>Hecatomb,</hi> by their Feet, not Heads: or count them by Scores, for in things without Heads Six-ſcore go to an Hnndred. They would be a New <hi>Septuagint;</hi> the Old tranſlated Scripture out of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berw</hi> into <hi>Greek,</hi> theſe turn in to <hi>four ſhillings a day.</hi> And and theſe <hi>Aſſemblers</hi> were begot in one day, as <hi>Hercules's</hi> fifty Baſtards all in one night. Their firſt Liſt was ſprinkled with ſome names of Honour, (Dr. <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> Dr. <hi>Morley</hi>-Dr. <hi>Hammond, &amp;e,</hi>) But theſe were <hi>Divines;</hi> too worthy to mix with ſuch <hi>ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Miniſters,</hi> and would not <hi>Aſſemble</hi> without the <hi>Royal Call.</hi> Nay, the firſt Liſt had one Archbiſhop, one Biſhop, and an Half, (for Biſhop <hi>Brownrigg</hi> was then but <hi>Elect.</hi>) But now their <hi>Aſſembly</hi> (as Philoſophers think the World) conſiſts of <hi>Atoms;</hi> petty ſmall Levites, whoſe <hi>Parts</hi> are not <hi>perceptible.</hi> And yet theſe inferior poſtern Teachers have intoxicated <hi>England</hi> (for a man ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times grow's drunk by a Gliſter.) When they all meet, they ſhew Beaſts in <hi>Aſrick</hi> by promiſcuous coupling engender Monſters. Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> viſit's them (as <hi>Perſians</hi> uſe) to ſee <hi>wild Aſſes</hi> fight: when the <hi>Commons</hi> have tyr'd him with their new Law, theſe Bretheren refreſh him with their mad Goſpel: They lately were gravell'd 'twixt <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Jerico;</hi> they knew not the diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance 'twixt thoſe two places; one cry'd twenty miles, another ten, 'twas con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded ſeven, for this reaſon, that <hi>Fiſh was brought from</hi> Jericho <hi>to</hi> Jeruſalem
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48253:3"/>
               <hi>market:</hi> Mr <hi>Selden</hi> ſmil'd and ſaid <hi>perhaps the Fiſh, was ſalt Fiſh</hi> and ſo ſtopp'd their mouths. Earl <hi>Philip</hi> goes thither to hear them <hi>ſpend;</hi> when he heard them toſs their <hi>National, Provincial, Claſſical, Congregational;</hi> he ſwore <hi>damnably,</hi> that a pack of good Dogs made better Muſick: His Alluſion was porper, ſince the <hi>Elder's Maid</hi> had a four-legg'd Husband. To ſpeak truth, this <hi>Aſſembly</hi> is the <hi>two Houſes</hi> Tiring-room where the <hi>Lords</hi> and the <hi>Commons</hi> put on their Viſards and Maſques of Religion. And their <hi>Honors</hi> have ſo <hi>ſifted</hi> the Church, that at laſt they have found the <hi>Bran</hi> of the Clergy. Yet ſuch poor Church-menders muſt Reform and ſhuffle: though they find Church Government may a thouſand wayes be changed for the worſe, but not one way for the better. Theſe have lately publiſh'd <hi>Annotations</hi> on the Bible, where their firſt Note (on the word <hi>CREATE</hi>) is a Libel againſt Kings for creating of Honors. Their <hi>Annotation</hi> on <hi>Jacob's</hi> two Kids, is, that <hi>two Kids are too much for one man's ſupper:</hi> but <hi>he had</hi> (ſay they) <hi>but one Kid and the other made Sauce.</hi> They obſerve upon <hi>Herod,</hi> what a Tyrant he was, to kill Infants under two years old, <hi>without</hi> giving <hi>them legal Trial,</hi> that they might ſpeake for themſelves. Commonly they follow the <hi>Geneva</hi> Margin, as thoſe Sea-men who underſtood not the <hi>Compaſs</hi> crept a long the Shore. But <hi>I</hi> hear they threaten a <hi>ſecond Edition,</hi> and in the interim thruſt forth a paultry <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> which expounds Nine <hi>Commandements,</hi> and Eleven Articles of the <hi>Creed.</hi> Of late they are much in love with <hi>Chronograms,</hi> becauſe (if poſſible) they are duller than <hi>Anagrams;</hi> O how they have torn the poor Biſhops names to pick out the number 666! little dreaming that a whole Bakers dozen of their own Aſſembly have that beaſtly number in each of their Names, and that as exactly as their <hi>Solemn League</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt's of 666 words. But though the <hi>Aſſembler's</hi> Brains are Lead, his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance is Braſs; for he damned ſuch as held two benefices, while him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf has four or five, beſides his Concubine <hi>Lecture.</hi> He is not againſt <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities,</hi> but <hi>Dualities;</hi> He ſays it is unlawful to have two of his own, though four of other mens; and obſerves how the Hebrew word for <hi>Life</hi> has no ſingular number. Yet it is ſome relief to a ſequeſtred perſon to ſee two <hi>Aſſemblers</hi> ſnarl for his Tithes; for of all kind of Beaſts none can match an <hi>Aſſembler</hi> but an <hi>Aſſembler.</hi> He never enters a Church by the Door, but clambers up through a Window of <hi>Sequeſtration,</hi> or ſteals in through Vaults and Cellars by Clandeſtine Contracts with an Expecting Patron. He is moſt ſure no Law can hurt him, for Laws dyed in <hi>England</hi> the year before the <hi>Aſſembler</hi> was born. The beſt way to hold him, is (as our King <hi>Richard</hi> bound the King of <hi>Cyprus</hi>) in <hi>ſilver chains.</hi> He loves to diſcourſe of the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> becauſe her ſtreets are of fine <hi>Gold;</hi> and yet could like <hi>London</hi> as well, were <hi>Cheapſide</hi> paved with the <hi>Philoſopher's ſtone.</hi> Nay, he would ſay his Prayers with <hi>Beads,</hi> if he might have a Set made of all Diamonds: This, this is it which tempts him to ſuch mad Articles againſt the <hi>Loyal Clergy,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:48253:3"/>whom he dreſſes as he would have them appear; juſt as the Ballad of <hi>Dr. Fauſtus</hi> brings forth the Devil in a <hi>Friars weed.</hi> He accuſed one Miniſter, for ſaying <hi>the bleſſed Virgin was the Mother of God,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Ancients call her.) Another he charged for a common Drunkard, whom all the Country knows has drunk nothing but Water theſe 26 years. But the <hi>Aſſembler</hi> himſelf can drink Widows Tears though their husbands are not dead. Sure, if <hi>Paracelſuſ's</hi> Doctrine were true, (that <hi>to cat creatures alive will perpetuate man's life</hi>) the <hi>Aſſembler</hi> were imortal, for he ſwallows quick Men, Wives, and Children; and devours <hi>Lives</hi> as well as <hi>Livings;</hi> as if he were born in that Pagan Province where <hi>None might marry till he had Killed twelve Chriſtians.</hi> This makes him kneel to Lieutenant General <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel</hi> (as <hi>Indians</hi> to the Devil;) for he ſaw how <hi>Oliver</hi> firſt threw—, then— and can with a wink do as much for—: Like <hi>Milo</hi> in the <hi>Olympicks,</hi> by practiſing on a <hi>Calf</hi> grew ſtrong enough for a <hi>Bull,</hi> and could with caſe give a lift to an <hi>Aſſe.</hi> The great Turk was ſending his Ambaſſador, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate the <hi>Aſſemblies</hi> Proceedings againſt the <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> He Ordered them Thanks for Licencing his <hi>Alcoran</hi> to be printed in <hi>Engliſh;</hi> but hearing <hi>Ottoman Cromwel</hi> had talked of <hi>marching to the Walls of Conſtantinople,</hi> that Embaſſy was ſtopt. The only difference 'twixt the <hi>Aſſembler</hi> and a <hi>Turk,</hi> is, that one plants Religion by the <hi>power of the Sword,</hi> and the other by the power of the <hi>Cymeter.</hi> Nay, the greateſt ſtrife in their whole Conventicle, is who ſhall do worſt; for they all intend to make the Church but a <hi>Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre,</hi> having not only <hi>Plunder'd</hi> but <hi>Anatomiz'd</hi> all the true Clergy; whoſe torment is hight'ned in being deſtroyed by ſuch dull inſtruments; as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> was ſawn to pieces with a <hi>wooden Saw.</hi> The <hi>Aſſembler</hi> wondèrs that the King and his Friends live ſtill in hope; he thinks them all in St. <hi>Clemens</hi>'s caſe, drown'd with an Anchor tyed about his neck. He has now got power to viſit the Univerſities; where theſe blinking <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors</hi> look on eminent Scholars (as the Blind-man who ſaw <hi>men</hi> like <hi>Trees</hi>) as Timber growing within the Root-and-Branch <hi>Ordinance.</hi> The <hi>Aſſembler</hi> has now left Scholars ſo poor, they have ſcarce Rags wherewith to make Paper. A man would think the <hi>Two houſes</hi> intend to tranſport the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities,</hi> ſince they load <hi>Aſſes</hi> with Colledge-Revenues. For though theſe <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblers</hi> made themſelves <hi>Heads,</hi> they are rather <hi>Hands</hi> of Colledges, for they all are takers, and take all. And yet they are ſuch creeping Tyrants, that Scholars are Expell'd the two <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> as the old <hi>Thracians,</hi> fore'd from their Countrey by Rats and Mice. So that Learning now is ſo much advanced, as <hi>Arrowſmith's</hi> Glaſs-eye ſees more then his natural. They never admit a good ſcholar to a Benefice, for the <hi>Aſſemblies</hi> Balance is the <hi>Lake</hi> of <hi>Sodom,</hi> where Iron ſwims and Feathers ſink. Their Divinity-Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations are with Women or Lay-men; and 'tis only on one Queſtion (<hi>Epiſcopacy</hi>) where the <hi>Aſſembler</hi> talks all that he and his friends can ſay,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48253:4"/>(though his beſt <hi>medium</hi> to prove <hi>Presbyters</hi> more antient than <hi>Biſhops,</hi> is, that <hi>Scribes, Phariſees, Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Elders</hi> where before the <hi>Apoſtels;</hi>) Yet if a Scholar or good Argument come, he flies them as much as if they were his Text. This made him curſe Dr. <hi>Steward,</hi> Dr. <hi>Laney</hi> and Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> and had he not had more Braſs in his Face than in his Kitchin, he had hang'd himſelf at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge,</hi> and ended with that <hi>Treaty.</hi> For he has naught of <hi>Logick,</hi> but her <hi>clutch'd ſiſt,</hi> and rail's at <hi>Philoſophy</hi> as Beggars do at Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen. He has very bad luck when he deals in <hi>Philologie,</hi> as one of them (and that no mean man) who in his preface to the Reader, ſayes, that St. <hi>Paul had read Euſtathius upon Homer,</hi> though the <hi>Apoſtle dyed a</hi> thouſand years before <hi>Euſtathius</hi> was born. The <hi>Aſſembers</hi> Dyet is ſtrangely different, for he dines wretchedly on dry Bread at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> four <hi>Aſſemblers</hi> for 13 pence: But this ſharpens and <hi>Whats him</hi> for ſupper, where he feeds gratis with his City-Landlord, to whom he brings a huge Stomach and News; for which Cramm'd Capons cram him. <hi>He</hi> ſcrews into Families where is ſome rich Daughter or Heir; but whoever takes him into their boſom, will dye like <hi>Cleopatra.</hi> VVhen it rains he is Coach'd (a <hi>Claſſis</hi> of them together) rouling his Eyes to mark who beholds him. His ſhorteſt things are his hair and his Cloack. His hair is cut to the figure of 3; two high Cliffs run up his Temples, whoſe Cap of ſhorn hair ſhoots down his Forehead, with Creeks indented, where his Ears ride at Anchor. Had this falſe Prophet been carryed with <hi>Habbakuk,</hi> the <hi>Angel</hi> had caught faſt hold of his <hi>Ears,</hi> and led him as he leads his Auditory. His Eyes are part of his Tithe at <hi>Eaſter,</hi> which he boyles at each Sermon. He has two Mouths, his Noſe is one, for he ſpeaks through both. His hands are not in his Gloves but his Gloves in his Hands, for 'cwixt ſweatings that is, Sermons, he handles little elſe, except his dear Mammon. His Gown (I mean his Cloak) reaches but his pockets: when he rides in that mantle, with a Hood on his ſhoulders and a hat above both, is he not then his own <hi>Man of ſin</hi> with the <hi>Triple Crown?</hi> you would ſwear ſome honeſt Carpenter dreſs'd him, and made him the Tunnel of a Country Chimney. His Doublet and Hoſe are of dark Blew, a grain deeper than pure <hi>Coventry:</hi> but of late he's in Black, ſince the Loyal Clergy were perſecuted into Colors. His two lo geſt things are his <hi>Nayls</hi> and his <hi>Prayer.</hi> But the cleaneſt thing about him is his <hi>Pulpit-Cuſhion,</hi> for he ſtill beats the Duſt out of it. To do him right. commonly he wears a pair of good Lungs, whereby he turns the Church into a Belfry, for his Clapper makes ſuch a Din, you cannot hear the <hi>Cym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball</hi> for the <hi>Tinkling.</hi> If his pulpit be large he walks his Round, and ſpeaks as from a Garriſon, (his own Neck is Palizado'd with a Ruff) VVhen he firſt enters his prayer before Sermon, he winks and gaſps, and gaſps and winks, as if he prepared to preach in another world, He ſeems in a ſlumber, then in a Dream; then rumbles a while; at laſt ſounds forth, and then throws
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48253:4"/>ſo much Dirt and Non-ſence towards Heaven, as he durſt not offer to a Member of Parliament. Now becauſe Scripture bids him <hi>not curſe the King in</hi> his <hi>thought,</hi> he does it in his Pulpit by word of mouth; though heaven ſtrike him Dumb in the very Act, as it did <hi>Hill</hi> at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> who while he pray'd, <hi>Depoſe Him, O Lord, who would depoſe us,</hi> was made the <hi>dumb Devil.</hi> This (one would think) ſhould <hi>gargle</hi> his foul mouth. For his only hope why God ſhould hear him againſt the King, is the Devil himſelf (that great <hi>Aſſembler</hi>) was heard againſt <hi>Job.</hi> His whole prayer is ſuch an irrational Bleating, that (without a Metaphor) 'tis the <hi>Calves of his Lipps:</hi> And commonly 'tis larded with fine new words, as <hi>Savingable, Muchly, Chriſt-Jeſuſnes,</hi> &amp;c. and yet he has the face to preach againſt <hi>Prayer in an unknown Tongue.</hi> Sometimes he is founder'd, and then there is ſuch hideous Coughing: But that is very ſeldom, for he can glibly run over Non-ſence, as an empty Cart trundles down a Hill. VVhen the King girt round the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> at <hi>Leſtythiell,</hi> an <hi>Aſſembler</hi> complained that <hi>God had drawn his People into the Wilderneſs,</hi> and told Him, <hi>He was bound in honour to feed them; for, Lord,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>ſince, thou giveſt them no Meat, we pray thee, O Lord, to give them no Stomachs.</hi> He tore the <hi>Liturgie,</hi> becauſe, forſooth, it ſhackled his Spirit, (he would be a Devil without a <hi>circle;</hi>) and now if he ſee the Book of <hi>Common-prayer,</hi> the fire ſees it next, as ſure as the Biſhops were burned who compiled it. Yet he has mercy on <hi>Hopkins</hi> and <hi>Sternhold,</hi> becauſe their <hi>Meeters</hi> are ſung without Authority (no Statute, Canon, or Injunction at all;) only like himſelf, firſt crept into private houſes; and then into Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. Mr. <hi>Rous</hi> moved thoſe <hi>Meeters</hi> might be ſequeſtred, and his own new Rithmes to enjoy the ſequeſtration; but was refuſed becauſe <hi>John Hopkins</hi> was as ancient as <hi>John Calvin;</hi> Beſides, when <hi>Rous</hi> ſtood forth for his Trial, <hi>Robin Wiſdom</hi> was found the better Poet. 'Tis true, they have a <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory,</hi> but 'tis good for nothing but <hi>Adoniram,</hi> who ſold the <hi>Original</hi> for 400 <abbr>l.</abbr> And the Book muſt ſerve both <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> as the <hi>Directory Needle</hi> point's North and South. The <hi>Aſſembler's</hi> only ingenuity is, that he prays for an <hi>ex tempore</hi> Spirit, ſince his Conſcience tells him he has no Learning. His prayer thus ended, he then looks round, to obſerve the Sex of his Congregation, and accordingly turns the Apoſtle's Men, Fathers, and Brethren, into Dear Brethren and Siſters. For, his uſual Auditory is moſt-part Female; and as many Siſters flock to him, as at <hi>Paris</hi> on Saint <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets</hi> day, when all come to Church that are, or hope to be with child that year. He divides his Text as he did the Kingdom, makes one part fight againſt another: or as <hi>Burges</hi> divides the Dean of <hi>Paul's</hi> Houſe, not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to parts, but Tenements, that is, ſo as 'twill yield moſt money. And pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly they are Tenements, for each part muſt be dwelt upon, though himſelf comes near it but once a quarter; and ſo his Text is rather let out than <hi>Divided.</hi> Yet ſometimes (to ſhew his skill in <hi>Keckermen,</hi>) he <hi>Butchers</hi> a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48253:5"/>Text, cuts it (juſt as the <hi>Levite</hi> did his <hi>Concubine</hi>) into many dead parts, breaking the ſence and words all to pieces, and then they are not divided, but ſhattered like the Splinters of <hi>Don Quixot's</hi> Lance. If his Text be to the occaſion, his firſt Diſh is <hi>Apples of Gold, in Pictures of Silver;</hi> yet tells not the People what Pictures thoſe were. His Sermon and prayer grin at each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the one is <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> the other Independent, for he preaches up the <hi>Claſses,</hi> yet prays for the Army. Let his Doctrine and Reaſon be what they will, his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe is ſtill to ſave his Benefice and augment his Lecture.</hi> He talks much of <hi>Truth,</hi> but abhorrs <hi>Peace,</hi> leſt it ſtrip him as <hi>naked</hi> as <hi>Truth;</hi> and therefore hates a perſonal Treaty, unleſs with a Siſter. He has a rare ſimp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ering way of expreſſions he calls a Marryed Couple <hi>Saints that enjoy the miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> &amp; a man Drunk, is <hi>a Brother full of the Creature.</hi> Yet at Wedding Sermors he is very familiar, &amp; (like that Picture in the Church at <hi>Leyden</hi>) ſhews <hi>Adam</hi> &amp; <hi>Eve</hi> without <hi>Figleaves.</hi> At Funerals he gives infallible Signs that the Party is gone to Heaven, but his chief Mark of a <hi>child of God,</hi> is <hi>to be good to God's Miniſters.</hi> And hence it is he calls his Preachment <hi>Manna,</hi> fitted not to his hearers <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> but their <hi>Palat;</hi> for 'tis to feed himſelf, not them. If he chance to tire, he refreſhes himſelf with the Peoples Hum, as a Collar of Bells to chear up a Pack-horſe. 'Tis no wonder he'll preach, but that any will hear him, (and his conſtant Auditors do but ſhew the length of their Ears;) For he is ſuch an' A <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that to hear him makes good Scholars ſick, but to read him is death. Yet though you heard him three hours he'll ask a fourth, as the Beggar at <hi>Delph</hi> craves your Charity <hi>becauſe he cats four pound of Bread at a Meal.</hi> 'Twas from his Larum the <hi>Watch-makers</hi> learn'd their <hi>infinite Skrew.</hi> His Glaſs and Text are equaly handled, that is, once an hour: nay ſometimes be ſally's and never returns, and then we ſhould leave him to the Company of <hi>Lorimers,</hi> for he muſt be held with Bit and Bridle. Who ever once has been at his Church can never doubt the Hiſtory of <hi>Balaam.</hi> If he have got any new Tale or Expreſſion, 'tis eaſier to make ſtones ſpeak than him to hold his peace. He hates a Church where there is an <hi>Eccho,</hi> for it Robs him of his dear <hi>Repetition,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founds the Auditory as well as he. But of all Mortals I admire the <hi>Short-hand-men,</hi> who have the patience to write from his Mouth: had they the art to ſhorten it into Senſe, they might write his whole Sermon on the back of their Nail. For his Invention conſiſts in finding a way to ſpeak nothing upon any thing; and were he in the <hi>Grand Seignior's</hi> power, he would lodge him with his <hi>Mutes;</hi> for <hi>Nothing</hi> and <hi>Nothing to purpoſe</hi> are all one. <hi>I</hi> wonder in conſcience he can preach againſt <hi>Sleeping</hi> at his <hi>Opium</hi>-Sermons. He preaches indeed both in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon; for he rayl's at Popery; when the Land is almoſt loſt in Presbytery; and would cry out <hi>Fire, Fire,</hi> in <hi>Noah's Flood.</hi> Yet all this he ſo acts with his Hands, that in this ſence too his Preaching is an <hi>Handicraft.</hi> Nor can we complain that Plays
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48253:5"/>are put down while he can preach; ſave only his <hi>Sermons</hi> have worſe ſence and leſs truth. But he blew down the Stage and preach'd up the <hi>Scaffold.</hi> And very wiſely, leſt men ſhould track him, and find where he pilfers all his beſt <hi>Simile's,</hi> (the only thing wherein he is commendable, St <hi>Paul</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf having cull'd Sentences from <hi>Menander's Thais,</hi> though 'twas his worſt, that is, unchaſt Comedy.) Sometimes the <hi>Aſſembler</hi> will venture at the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal, and then (with the tranſlator of <hi>Don Quixot</hi>) he miſtakes <hi>Sobs</hi> and <hi>Sighs</hi> for <hi>Eggs</hi> and <hi>Collops.</hi> But commonly (for want of <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi>) he learns <hi>Hebrew,</hi> and ſtreight is <hi>illuminated;</hi> that is, mad: his Brain is broke by a Brickbat caſt from the Tower of <hi>Babel.</hi> And yet this empty windy Teacher has <hi>Lectur'd</hi> a War quite round the Kingdom: he has found a <hi>Circulation of blood</hi> for <hi>Deſtruction</hi> (as famous <hi>Harvey</hi> for <hi>Preſervation</hi>) of Mankind. 'Twas eaſie to foreſee a great Mortality, when Ravens were heard in all <hi>Corporations.</hi> For, as Multitude of Froggs preſage a Peſtilence, ſo croaking <hi>Lecturers</hi> foretold an <hi>Aſſembly.</hi> Men come to Church, as the Great <hi>Alexander</hi> went to Sacrifice, led by Crows. You have ſeen a ſmall <hi>Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree</hi> grow in chinks and clefts of Church-walls, it ſeems rather a <hi>Weed</hi> than a <hi>Tree;</hi> which, lend it growth, makes a Rent in the Wall, and throws down the Church. Is not this the <hi>Aſſembler?</hi> grown from Schiſms (which himſelf begot,) and if permitted, will make the Church but a <hi>Floor</hi> or <hi>Church-yard.</hi> Yet, for all this, he will be call'd <hi>Chriſt's Miniſter</hi> and Saint, as the Rebells againſt King <hi>John</hi> were the <hi>Army of God.</hi> Sure when they meet they cannot but ſmile; for the dulleſt amongſt them needs muſt know that they all cheat the people; ſuch groſs, low impoſtors, that we die the death of the Emperor <hi>Claudius,</hi> poyſon'd by <hi>Muſhromes.</hi> The old Hereticks had Skill &amp; Learning (ſome excuſe for a Seduced Church; thoſe were <hi>Scholars,</hi> but theſe <hi>Aſſemblers;</hi> whoſe very Brains (as <hi>Manichaeus's</hi> skin) are ſtuff'd with <hi>Chaff.</hi> For they ſtudy little, &amp; preach much, ever ſick of a <hi>Diabetes:</hi> nor do they <hi>read,</hi> but <hi>weed</hi> Authors, picking up cheap &amp; refuſe Notes, that with <hi>Caligula</hi> they gather Cockle-ſhells, &amp; with <hi>Domitian</hi> retire into their Studie to catch Flies. At <hi>Faſts</hi> &amp; <hi>Thank ſgivings</hi> the <hi>Aſſembler</hi> is the <hi>State's</hi> Trumpet; for then he doth not <hi>preach,</hi> but is <hi>blown;</hi> proclaims News very loud, the Trumpet and his Forehead being both of one Metall. (And yet, good man, he ſtill prays for <hi>Boldneſs.</hi>) He hackneys out his Voice like a Cryer; and is a kind of <hi>Spiritual Agitant,</hi> receives Orders, and ſpreads them. In earneſt the <hi>States</hi> can't want this Tool, for without him the <hi>Saints</hi> would ſcarce <hi>Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> And if the Zealots chance to fly out, they are charm'd home by this <hi>Sounding Braſs.</hi> There is not on earth a baſer Sycophant; for he ever is chewing ſome <hi>Vote</hi> or <hi>Ordinance;</hi> and tells the People how <hi>ſavoury</hi> it is; like him who lick'd up the Emperor's ſpittle and ſwore 'twas ſweet. Would the <hi>two Houſes</hi> give him <hi>Cathedral Lands,</hi> he would prove <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> to be <hi>Jure Divino:</hi> but ſhould they offer him the <hi>Self-denying-Ordinance,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:48253:6"/>he would juſtifie the Devil and curſe them to their faces, (his Brother Kirk-man did it in <hi>Scotland.</hi>) 'Tis pleaſant to obſerve how finely they play into each others hands; <hi>Marſhall</hi> procures thanks to be given to <hi>Sedg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> (for his great pains) <hi>Sedgwick</hi> obtains as much for <hi>Marſhall,</hi> and ſo they all pimp for one another. But yet (to their great comfort be it ſpoken) their whole ſeven years Sermons at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> are now to be ſold in <hi>Fetter-lane</hi> and <hi>Pyecorner.</hi> Before a Battall the <hi>Aſſembler</hi> ever ſpeaks to the Souldiers; and the holding up of his hands muſt be as neceſſary as <hi>Moſes</hi>'s againſt the <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lekites:</hi> For he pricks them on, tells them that <hi>God loves none but the valiant:</hi> but when Bullets flye, Himſelf runs firſt, and then crys <hi>All the ſons of</hi> Adam <hi>are cowards!</hi> Were there any <hi>Metempſychoſis</hi> his Soul would want a Lodgiog; no ſingle Beaſt could fit him, being wiſe as a Sheep and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent as a Wolf. His ſole comfort is, he cannot out-ſin <hi>Hugh Peters:</hi> Sure, as Satan hath poſſeſſed the <hi>Aſſembler,</hi> ſo <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> hath poſſeſſed Satan, and is the Devi's Devil. He alone would fill a whole Herd of <hi>Gadarens.</hi> He hath ſuck'd Blood ever ſince he lay in the <hi>Butcher's</hi> Sheets: and now (like his <hi>Sultan</hi>) has a Shambles in his Countenance; ſo crimſon and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid, you may there read how St. <hi>Laurence</hi> dyed, and think <hi>the three Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> were delivered from his face. This is St. <hi>Hugh,</hi> who will <hi>Levell</hi> the <hi>Aſſembler,</hi> or the <hi>Devil's an Aſſe.</hi> Yoke theſe Brethren; and they two cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple like a <hi>Sadducee</hi> and a <hi>Phariſae,</hi> or a <hi>Turk</hi> and a <hi>Perſian,</hi> both Mahume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans. But the <hi>Aſſembler's</hi> deepeſt, higheſt Abomination, is his <hi>Solemn Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue and Covenant;</hi> whereby he ſtrives to <hi>damn</hi> or <hi>begger</hi> the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; out-doing the Devil, who onely <hi>perſuades,</hi> but the <hi>Aſſembler forces</hi> to <hi>perjury</hi> or <hi>ſtarving.</hi> And this) whoever lives to obſerve it) will one day ſink both him and his Faction: for he and his <hi>Oath</hi> are ſo much one, that were he halfhang'd and let down again, his firſt word would be <hi>Covenant! Covenant!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I forget, a <hi>Character</hi> ſhould be brief (though <hi>tedious Length</hi> be his beſt Character.) Therefore I'll give ye' (what He denyes the Sequeſterd Clergy) but a <hi>fifth Part.</hi> For weigh him ſingle, and he has the Pride of three Tyrants, the Forehead of ſix Gaolers and the Fraud of twelve Brokers. Or take him in the Bunch, and their whole <hi>Aſſembler</hi> is a <hi>Club</hi> of Hypocrites, where ſix dozen of Schiſmatik-ſpends two hours for four ſhillings apiece.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48253:6"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
